let set14 =
    [
        {
            question: `#1. Where was the first oil well of the world drilled?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Pennsylvania',
                    'B. Pittsburgh',
                    'C. Assam',
                    'D. London',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: The world’s first oil well was drilled in Pennsylvania, USA, in 1859. Eight years later, in 1867, oil was found at Makum in Assam.In India, oil is found in Assam, Gujarat, Mumbai High and in the river basins of Godavari and Krishna.`
        },
        {
            question: `#2. Naphthalene balls, used to combat moths and other pests, is obtained from which of the following?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Coke',
                    'B. Coal tar',
                    'C. Coal gas',
                    'D. CNG',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Naphthalene balls are obtained from coal tar. Coke, coal tar and goal gas are all obtained from coal.Natural gas is stored, under high pressure as compressed natural gas (CNG).India has vast reserves of natural gas. Natural gas has been found in Tripura, Rajasthan, Maharashtra and in the Krishna (Godavari delta).`
        },
        {
            question: `#3. Consider the following statements regarding combustion and ignition temperature? \n 1. Oxygen is required for the combustion of materials.Heat and light are given out in this process. \n 2. The lowest temperature at which a substance (fuel) catches fire is called its ignition temperature. \n 3. The combustion of phosphorus occurs at room temperature, in the presence of air. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 and 2 only',
                    'B. 2 and 3 only',
                    'C. 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D,`,
            exp: `Explanation: The way food is broken down in the human body, on reaction with oxygen, to give out energy; substances react with oxygen during combustion and give out heat and light. The lowest temperature at which a substance catches fire is called its Ignition temperature. The ignition temperature of phosphorus is so low, that it catches fire in room temperature, in the presence of air.`
        },
        {
            question: `#4. Consider the following statements in context of safety matches: \n 1. A mixture of Antimony Trisulphide and Potassium Chlorate is applied on the heads of matchsticks. \n 2. The rubbing surface has powdered glass and a little white phosphorus. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 and 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: A mixture of Antimony Trisulphide and Potassium Chlorate is applied on the heads of matchsticks. Earlier, white phosphorus was also used along with these two chemicals, but due to its harmful effects, its use was discontinued in the manufacture of safety matches. The rubbing surface has powdered glass and a little red phosphorus.. When the match is struck against the rubbing surface, some red phosphorus gets converted into white phosphorus. This immediately reacts with Potassium Chlorate in the matchstick head to produce enough heat to ignite Antimony Trisulphide and start the combustion.`
        },
        {
            question: `#5. The job of a fire extinguisher is to cut off the supply of air, or to bring down the temperature of the fuel, or both. Consider the following statements in the context of cutting off the supply of air: \n 1. Water vapours, formed due to water being poured on the flame, surround the combustible material, helping in cutting off the supply of air. \n 2. CO2, being heavier than oxygen, covers the fire like a blanket. Since the contact between the fuel and oxygen is cut off, the fire is controlled. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 nor 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Water cools the combustible and the water vapours formed also surround the combustible material, cutting off the supply of air. thus, the fire is extinguished. The most common fire extinguisher is water. But for fires involving electrical equipment and inflammable materials like petrol, carbon dioxide (CO2) is the best extinguisher. CO2, being heavier than oxygen, covers the fire like a blanket. Since the contact between the fuel and oxygen is cut off, the fire is controlled. It does not harm the electrical equipment. CO2 can be stored at high pressure as a liquid in cylinders. When released from the cylinder, CO2 expands enormously in volume and cools down. Another way to get CO2 is to release a lot of dry powder of chemicals like sodium bicarbonate (baking soda) or potassium bicarbonate. On coming near the fire, these chemicals decompose to give off CO2.`
        },
        {
            question: `#6. Of the following statements, which of the following is/are correct regarding candle flames? \n 1. Unburnt carbon particles are present in the luminous zone of the flame. \n 2. The non-luminous zone of the flame has a highest temperature.`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 nor 2',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: The substances which vapourise on combustion, produce flame. The flame produced during the combustion of candle has three parts: non luminous zone, luminous zone and non combustible zone. Unburnt carbon particles are present in the luminous zone of the flame. The non luminous zone of the candle flame has the highest temperature. It is the outermost region of the flame, which is blue in colour.`
        },
        {
            question: `#7. Consider the following statements: \n 1. Incomplete combustion of fuels produce the poisonous gas, carbon dioxide. \n 2. Excessive proportion of carbon dioxide in the environment results in global warming. \n 3. Oxides of sulfur and nitrogen mix with rain, and result in acid rain. \n Which of the above statement/statements is/are correct?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Only 1 and 2',
                    'B. Only 2 and 3',
                    'C. Only 3',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Incomplete combustion of fuels produce carbon monoxide. It is an extremely poisonous gas.Combustion of most fuels give out carbon dioxide in the environment, the excessive quantity of which, results in global warming.Combustion of coal and petrol give out sulfur dioxide. It is an extremely suffocating and caustic gas. Moreover, petrol engines give off gaseous oxides of nitrogen. Oxides of sulphur and nitrogen dissolve in rain water and form acids. Such rain is called acid rain. It is very harmful for crops, buildings and soil.CNG produces the oxides of sulfur and nitrogen in very small amounts.`
        },
        {
            question: `#8. Assertion (A): In India, 98% of the coal is found in Gondwana rocks of Moran region. \n Reason (R): The main regions of Gondwana rocks are found in West Bengal, Jharkhand and Odisha.`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A',
                    'B. Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A',
                    'C. A is true but R is false',
                    'D. Both A & R is not true',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Around 67 % of total commercial energy produced in India and 98% of India's total account is found in Gondwana rocks of Moran region. The main regions of Gondwana rocks are found in West Bengal, Jharkhand and Odisha. There are four types of coal found in India: Anthracite (Best quality of coal found only in Jammu & Kashmir); Bituminous (Second best quality of coal); Lignite (Found in Tamil Nadu, Rajasthan, Gujarat and Jammu & Kashmir). Coal accounts for approx. 67 % of total commercial energy produced in India and 98% of India’s total account is found in Gondwana rocks of Moran region. The main regions of Gondwana rocks are found in West Bengal, Jharkhand and,  Odisha. The first effort made to extract coal with modern technology in India was at Ranigunj coal region in West Bengal. Types of coal on the basis of carbon content: Anthracite is the best quality of coal which carries 80 to 95 per cent carbon content. It ignites slowly with a blue flame. It has the highest calorific value. It is found in small quantity in Jammu and Kashmir. Bituminous carries 60 to 80 per cent of carbon content and a low level of moisture content. It is widely used and has high calorific value. It is found in Jharkhand, West Bengal, Odisha, Chhattisgarh and Madhya Pradesh. Lignite is often brown in colour. It carries 40 to 55 per cent carbon content. It is an intermediate stage which happens during the alteration of woody matter into coal. It has high moisture content so it gives smoke when burnt. It is found in Rajasthan, Lakhimpur (Assam), and Tamil Nadu. Peat has less than 40 per cent carbon content. It is in the first stage of transformation from wood to coal. It has low calorific value and burns like wood.`
        },
        {
            question: `#9. The major constituent of biogas is:`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Methane',
                    'B. Ethane',
                    'C. Propane',
                    'D. Butane',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Biogas comprises primarily methane (CH4) and carbon dioxide (CO2) and may have small amounts of hydrogen sulphide (H2S), moisture and siloxanes.`
        },
        {
            question: `#10. Carbonisation is a process in which`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Dead vegetation convert into coal',
                    'B. Dead marine organisms convert into petroleum',
                    'C. Carbondioxide convert into carbon',
                    'D. none of these',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Carbonization is a slow pyrolysis process in which biomass is converted into a highly carbonaceous, charcoal-like material. Typically, carbonization consists of heating the biomass in an oxygen-free or oxygen-limited environment, and reaction conditions are tailored to maximize the production of char. Traditionally, charcoal production is one of the oldest chemical conversion processes known to mankind. Even today, charcoal production continues on a large scale worldwide, and is still making,  use—in part—of tradition charcoal kilns. Furthermore, there is renewed interest to carbonization, both from a scientific and a commercial point of view, for the production and application of biochar and torrefied biomass. This chapter gives an overview of carbonization, its chemistry, and the physicochemical properties of the resulting products. It also highlights the effects of feedstock properties and process conditions and concludes with an overview of traditional and modern carbonization techniques.`
        }
    ]